I went to Cedric's late one afternoon expecting the unexpected and sure enough I got
the unexpected.
It was an empty office, nobody else was there but Cedric.
No hint that it was an architect's office at all.
It was a black and grey room, no architectural models, no drawings lying around.
There was what looked as if it could have been a drawing board with a black cover on
it giving nothing away at all.
And Cedric was there very much with his big presence, a looming figure, somebody
looking
quite important, very sure of himself, charming man, very friendly, put me at ease
straight
away.
sat down, went through the work I'd brought along and he offered me a job
there and then, which was great. When he offered me the job I said, wow thank you
very much, yes please, I'll take it straight away. It was like an
unbelievable opportunity, I'd always wanted to work for him but never thought
it was worth writing in out of the blue because he must be inundated with
inquiries and he made me a fair financial offer which quite surprised me.
I was really keen to work for him I'd always idolized what I'd seen of his
work published in the various magazines and books and he was one of the
inspirational figures that I just wanted to work for. Cedric was very much a
bon viveur. He looked like he enjoyed life and I think he did. He often had his
cigar, his trademark cigar. He liked his brandy very much as well, often drinking
it a bit too early in the morning but that was Cedric. He was very warm, very
generous. I never saw him lose his temper. For an architect he was actually very
very calm. I never saw Cedric really being sad at all. He was always full of
anticipation
of the future. Never really looked back, always looked ahead. Great belief in what
the future
would bring. I think he had his frustrations because he hadn't built much and I
think that
was very sad. I think he really wanted to build. Everything that he did and the way
he did it led me to believe he did want to build. The projects were very thoroughly
researched
from the outset, a lot of site analysis, a lot of brief analysis, a lot of
challenging the brief,
an awful lot of studies as we can see through the archives on all of the projects,
everything
explored in the minutest detail. I don't believe he'd have done that had he not
thought the
the projects would go ahead.
But sadly, and it's not unusual, it happens to every architect,
an awful lot of the projects they work on never go ahead.
I was there with Cedric for two years,
and during that time we worked on a wide range of projects.
The sort of biggest was South Bank's study for GLC.
There was the Parc de Villette competition in Paris,
which he didn't win, which Bernard Schumi won.
there was going down the scale Battersea Power Station which I suspect he never
really thought
he would win but it was a fantastic proposal that he made. A small aircraft hangar
BA
there was a housing scheme in Australia for Alistair McAlpine and the Cedric Price
Aviary
they were the main ones. Battersea Power Station or BATHAT as he called the
competition was was a building that's that's been lying dormant for years it
has like lay dormant for many years before the competition the competition
was was launched I think Cedric thought nothing would happen for for a good many
years and in the end he was proved right I think he felt that what was important
the building was the view on the skyline, the chimneys and the part of the
structure immediately beneath that, so he left that and basically took the rest
out. It was a cover for creating potential for future users and so on at
that time undefined and I think he was proved right, you know the project, the
site lay dormant for the next 30 years, it's still empty, it's about to be
developed but it took a lot of boom and busts and developers going bankrupt
before anything is now finally happening and it's only now happening thanks to
the London boom and the absurdly high property prices in London that enable
these more difficult sites to finally be developed and it's a shame it's for a
largely housing based scheme rather than public uses. When I joined the office I
was the only architect working for Cedric there was there was a secretary
me and Cedric. So I was the assistant and when a project came in whether it was a
new project or a competition I would go about doing the analysis, visiting the
site, doing the site survey, all the things an architect does. We'd then sit
down and go through the competition brief, go through all the data I'd got
and so on. And generally what would happen is Cedric would then go away and
think. Office hours were 8 to 3. We arrived at 8 in the morning, rolled up the
silver
roll of lines, made some coffee, Cedric would come in soon after. Often I'd find on
my desk
a pile of drawings he'd done the night before and that's often how he worked. So he
would
work in his own quiet time, put a pile of drawings on the desk and then at some
point
during the day we'd go through them and I'd then develop the drawings and then we'd
sit
down again another day, go through it, chat, he'd have a think, respond and so it
continued.
The White Room was very much Cedric's domain, it's where he entertained his
visitors. In
In the morning he would come in, he'd do the post, then make a number of phone
calls, and
often during the day visitors would come in and out.
Raina Bannam was a frequent visitor, Joan Littlewood, Monica Pidgeon, Paul Finch,
Alistair
McAlpine, a long, long list of his close friends and contacts.
He'd always take them upstairs.
Alistair would often come round for breakfast, always have a bacon butty.
We generally didn't go up to the White Room.
We might go up to the White Room if Cedric had been working up there
and there was a lot of sketches to come, to bring down.
But it was his domain, his private world.
He kept his world separate.
There was the world of his office.
There was his close friends, Alford, Henderson, Frank Newby.
And then there was the world of the other architects, the AA.
And they were all very much pigeonholed and kept separate.
I'm not sure why Cedric kept those three different realms but they did come
together.
Once a year at Christmas he threw a very lavish Christmas party and people from the
three
different worlds were brought together and at election time, general election time,
he'd
throw an election party and then there again the three worlds might come together.
Otherwise they were kept separate.
The South Bank project was commissioned by Tony Banks, who was head of culture at
the
Greater London Council and one of Cedric's close friends. The South Bank was in a
very
sad state. It's an area the size of Covent Garden and Soho put together. It
contained
County Hall, which was the headquarters of the Greater London Council. It contained
Shell's
headquarters, National Theatre, Royal Festival Hall, the Film Museum.
The public realm between them was sort of empty, abandoned, unloved, dangerous at
night.
And Tony Banks was keen for Cedric to sort of cast his eye over it
and come up with a master plan for enhancing that key site in the heart of London.
So it was quite a long process, an awful lot of analysis,
many, many meetings. Cedric attended meeting after meeting after meeting with all
the various
interested parties. And after about six, nine months, we came up with the proposals
which
I think were good urban design proposals about networks of public routes, uses for
the spaces,
hierarchies and I guess the headline grabber was a giant ferris wheel next to County
Hall
which ultimately was built by another architect. The project
took the form of drawings, reports, number of documents, presentations and it was
handed over
to the GLC and nothing really came of it in the end. It wasn't the first project by
the
GLC that nothing came of for that site, there'd been project after project after
project.
I think it was so politically charged that it was going to be one of those projects
that
was going to be very difficult to see the light of day. And in the end it sort of
happened,
improvements have happened piecemeal but there's never, none of the projects looking
at the
site-wide have ever happened. For me, one of the highlights was the office parties.
When we got a glimpse into Cedric's other worlds, the General Election Party in
particular
were amazing, amazing things. His political friends would drop in and out, his AA
friends,
Eleanor, the people from the office, ex-members of staff. Cedric's brother would be
there
with a thing called a penguinometer, which was a swingometer,
which would swing according to whether Labour or the Conservatives were in power.
I used BBC data and programmed a Sinclair ZX81 computer
to make election projections.
The year I was there was when Margaret Thatcher was re-elected for a second time.
So given Cedric and his friends' more socialist tendencies,
it ended up not being a very jolly occasion,
but it was very interesting to get an insight into Cedric's life.
Cedric's one of these people that I've never seen being really vulnerable.
He's always been completely in control of the situation.
I think Cedric's stature helped.
His incredible intellect helped.
I think it was very difficult for people to attack him.
He was obviously a very controversial figure, enjoyed winding people up, enjoyed
coming
out with extraordinary statements sometimes like perhaps York Minster should be
demolished
or I think it was Cedric who once told the clients I've been through all the data
you've
given me and I don't think a new building will help your problem.
Cedric always talked about the role of the architect being to enable rather than to
build
and there are probably a number of interpretations of that. For me the enabler is
possibly can
be explained by Fun Palace where the only permanent part of the building of Fun
Palace
was really the structure and arguably the crane. So it wasn't really a building at
all.
parts of the building committed a huge range of activities to be supported
through the use of projection screens, through the use of demountable elements,
through the use of cabins and that in its totality created what was the Fun
Palace with its various concert halls, its exhibitions, its screens and so on.
but the building itself was just the structure and the crane.
I guess I'm not the only one to say that the favourite Cedric project was Fun
Palace.
I think it was extraordinary the impact it's had on the architectural profession
and what was considered quite amazing at that time is now standard practice
or became standard practice, the use of a structural framework rather than
load-bearing walls,
the incredible use of technology, the use of prefabricated elements, the use of
kitted parts,
demountable elements, the large projection screens which didn't exist then,
the sort of foresight he had was quite incredible.
And all those elements came to be standard practice for the generation that followed
him,
him, the Rogers, Foster, Sterling, Grimshaw and currently used by all the spin-offs
from those four practices. I think you can see traces of Cedric's
philosophy and approach in many of the projects of Foster, Rogers, Grimshaw,
Hopkins and of all the various spin-off practices that have come from those four
main practices over the years. You know obviously Pompidou Center in a watered
down version of Fun Palace, obviously in the whole kit of parts approach used by
Sterling, by Foster Rogers and Grimshaw. I think Cedric taught us all to think
laterally and the importance of that of looking beyond the box not not being
pigeonholed and possibly the way we're all we've all been trained at many
schools of architecture around the world
he taught us to unleash possibilities not to take things for granted to an
architecture should be a way of enabling things to happen often in an
undetermined way. He certainly taught us that architecture isn't all about
stylistic interventions and trophy architecture and unfortunately I think
there's been too much of that with the rise of the superstar architect. There's
there's been less of the, far too little importance placed on the lessons we've all
learnt from
Cedric but they're still all relevant and fortunately still all practised.
For me the most important question to ask about Cedric Price is why didn't he build
more? I think there's a common conception that he was quite happy not building but I
I think he really wanted to build and he'd have liked to have built a lot more.
He was a very good communicator, very good indeed.
His projects were widely published in the press and so on.
He didn't have a PR department, he didn't have press people handling it, he did it
all
himself.
He was very hands on as he was in every aspect of the practice and his work was
widely published.
and I think he became very influential through all of that and I think many believed
his ideas were right,
they were enthusiastic about his ideas, adopted them, built them,
so I think Cedric was probably very happy to see his ideas come to fruition, but
very disappointed he didn't do it himself.